A Guide to The Independent Correspondence and Other Materials, 1680-1936
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Collection of The Independent Correspondence and Other Materials 1680-1936
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 83
1 Hollinger Document Case
unknown
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Unknown provenance. Some of the papers were discovered in the 1980s among a collection of rare books owned by the Old Dominion University library which had been purchased from a New York City bookstore in 1971.
Biographical Information
The Independent was a New York weekly newspaper founded in 1848 by Henry Chandler Bowen. The Congregationalist journal, which was published until 1921, included social topics, primarily opposition to slavery and religious articles, but after the Civil War included literary submissions. Editors included, among others, Henry Ward Beecher, Theodore Tilton, Kinsley Twining, Hamilton Holt, William Hayes Ward, and his sister, Susan Hayes Ward.
William Hayes Ward (1835-1916) was born in Abingdon, Massachusetts, on June 25, 1835. He graduated with distinction from Amherst College in 1856 and from Andover Theological seminary in 1859. He married Ellen Maria Dickinson in 1859. Dr. Ward served as a professor of Latin at Ripon College in Wisconsin and was a prominent orientalist and biblical scholar in his later years. In 1868 he left Ripon College to join the editorial staff of The Independent. In 1884, he led an expedition to Babylonia to examine archeological sites, and became president of the American Oriental Society, a position held twice, from 1890-1894 and 1909-1910. He specialized in studying designs of Babylonian and Assyrian seal cylinders, which were used in ancient record-keeping.
Showing a lifelong concern for social issues in the newspaper and in private life, William Hayes Ward upheld African-American rights and opened the first conference held by the NAACP in 1909 in New York City. He was editor-in-chief of The Independent from 1896-1913 and is known for supporting poet Sidney Lanier, whose work was frequently published in the paper, and about whom Dr. Ward wrote a biographical memoir.
Horace Howard Furness, Sr., 1833-1912, was an important American Shakespeare scholar. He was known for his editing of Shakespeare's plays, which contained numerous editions of plays as well as criticism. His son, Horace Howard Furness, Jr., 1865-1930, was a partner and successor of his father's work and edited his letters. Samuel Chew was a renowned literary critic in the early twentieth century.
Scope and Content
The collection includes papers ranging in dates from 1680 to 1936 with the bulk of the collection falling between 1879 and 1881. Most of the collection is comprised of the correspondence of William Hayes Ward, editor of The Independent, with notable literary and historical figures including General John Charles Frémont, American explorer and expedition leader; P. T. Barnum, showman; and Asa Gray, the preeminent American botanist of the 19th century.
Other items in the collection include American literature and theater papers; colonial historical manuscripts and documents; and correspondence with the library of Norfolk division of the College of William and Mary (the predecessor of Old Dominion University).
Assorted other papers in the collection include presidential signatures; a letter by John Ruskin, Victorian art and social critic; part of a book manuscript by American author Washington Irving; colonial deeds, including a land grant signed and sealed by Lord Dunmore; and papers and letters on American theatre, including correspondence of Horace Howard Furness, Sr., Horace Howard Furness, Jr., and Samuel Chew.
The collection contains a number of transcriptions, some of which include inaccurate identifications which are noted in the finding aid.
Arrangement
The Historical Letters collection is divided into five series:
Series I, Editorial Correspondence of The Independent, 1866-1917
Series II, Literary Authors and Papers on American Theater, 1896-1913
Series III, Historical Manuscripts and Documents, 1680-1795
Series IV, Miscellaneous Literary and Political Correspondence, 1930-1936
Series V, William and Mary Norfolk Campus library Correspondence, 1958-1960
Contents List
- Editorial Correspondence of The Independent 1866-1917
  Editorial Correspondence of The Independent includes letters to the editors. Arrangement is the original order of letters found in a scrapbook, which the creator organized roughly by subject.
  - Scrapbook, Page 1. 1866. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - From Bayard Taylor to My Dear Sir. July 18, 1866.
  - Scrapbook, Page 2. 1880-1881. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Seal of North American Construction Company Puerto Cabella.
    - From J. T. Trowbridge to W. H. Ward. December 15, 1880.
    - From J. T. Trowbridge to W. H. Ward. January 5, 1881.
    - From General Charles Frémont to Mr. Bowen (Henry Chandler Bowen). Oct. 31, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 3. 1880. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Signature of Charles Sumner.
    - Business card. United States Coast Survey Office, Capt. of Eng'rs, As't in Charge.
    - Signature of U. S. President J. A. Garfield.
    - Signature of Louis Kingsley, Lieutenant and Executive Officer.
    - From Henry M. Hoyt to Henry C. Bowen. November 19, 1880.
    - From E. C. Stedman to W. H. Ward. June 29, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 4. 1880. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - To "Dear Sir" from S. Newcomb (Simon Newcomb). Nov. 23, 1880.
    - To "Gentlemen" from Lewis Swift. September 28, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 5. 1880. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - To W. H. Ward from James McCosh. No date.
    - To William H. Ward from James H. Fairchild. November 15, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 6. 1880-1881. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - To W. H. Ward from Leonard Bacon. Jan. 13, 1881.
    - To "My Dear Sir" from J. W. Nicer. June 20, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 7. 1880-1881. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - To W. H. Ward from Justin McCarthy. January 15, 1881.
    - To Editor of The Independent from Epes Sargent. November 24, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 8. 1880-1881. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - To W. H. Ward from Timothy Dwight. July 27, 1881.
    - To W. H. Ward from W. D. Whitney. November 26, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 9. 1880. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - To Henry C. Bowen from Charles W. Eliot. November 17, 1880.
    - To Henry C. Bowen from Horace Maynard. December 9, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 10. 1880. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - To W. H. Ward from Joseph Cook. November 8, 1880.
    - To Editor of The Independent from P. T. Barnum. July 17, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 11. 1880. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - To W. H. Ward from Asa Gray. February 1, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from Asa Gray. August 2, 1880.
    - To Editor of The Independent from Asa Gray. August 4, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from Asa Gray. September 2, 1880.
    - To Henry C. Bowen from Alexander H. Stephens. November 21, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 12. 1880. (Box-folder 1:12)
    - To My Dear Friends from Stephen [last name illegible]. February 26, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from T. De Witt Talmage. No date.
  - Scrapbook, Page 13. 1879-1880. (Box-folder 1:13)
    - To William H. Ward from Harriet P. Spofford. November 5, 1880.
    - To Editor of the Independent from James Freeman Clarke. November 6, 1879.
  - Scrapbook, Page 14. 1879-1880. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - To W. H. Ward from Howard Crosby. February 23, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from R. S. Storrs. Oct. 15, 1879.
    - To W. H. Ward from R. S. Storrs. December 16, [no year].
  - Scrapbook, Page 15. 1880. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - To W. H. Ward from Joseph Cook. August 24, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from [unreadable]. Feb. 22, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 16. 1880. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - To W. H. Ward from H. E. Scudder. March 22, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from H. E. Scudder. Sept. 6, 1880.
    - To Sir from [unreadable]. Dec. 7, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 17. 1880. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - To W. H. Ward from John Sherman. June 24, 1880.
    - To W. H. Ward from John Sherman. June 15, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 18. 1880. (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Envelope addressed to Dr. S. B. Ward from Grover Cleveland. No date.
    - Scrap with signature of U. S. Grant, U. S. President. No date.
    - To Dr. Ward from Mary Clemmer. Nov. 9, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 19. 1880. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - To Editor Independent from Abby Morton Diaz. June 25, [no year].
    - To Dr. W. H. Ward from Rose Terry Cooke. July 26, 1880.
  - Scrapbook, Page 20. 1881. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - To Dr. Ward from Grace Greenwood (Mrs. Lippincott). Jan. 22, 1881.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Harriet P. Spofford. June 17, [no year].
    - Manuscript of a poem entitled "Faithful." [In pencil identified as by Rose Terry Cooke.] No date.
  - Scrapbook, Page 21. 1880. (1:21 1:21)
    - To Mr. Ward from Lucy Stone. June 7, 1880.
    - Manuscript entitled "Strange Country," a poem. Signed Mr. S. M. B. Piatt. [Poet Sarah Morgan Bryan.] No date.
  - Scrapbook, Page 22. 1880. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - To Henry C. Bowen from Benjamin F. Butler. Nov. 19, 1880.
  - Loose items not in scrapbook. 1879-1917. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - To W. H. Ward from S. E. Wallace. Nov. 21, 1879.
    - To W. H. Ward from Helen Hunt Jackson. No date.
    - To The editor of The Independent from Rose Hawthorne Lathrop. November, 1880.
    - From W. H. Ward to Miss Jeffries. January 24, 1881.
    - To Sir from Sidney Lanier. July 19, 1880.
    - To My Dear Solomon from Herbert B. Tree. Feb. 7, 1917.
    - To Editor Independent from Wendell Phillips. No date.
    - To W. H. Ward from Edward S. Hale. June 22, 1880.
    - To My dear Dr. from J. W. Miller (Cincinnatus Hiner). Feb. 3, 1881.
    - From P. T. Barnum to Editor of the Independent. July 13, 1880.
  - Loose items not in scrapbook. 1879-1881. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Index of names. No date.
    - Note with name and address of Mrs. D. H. Cole. Note indicating contents are from the estate of the Misses Elmira and Mayrea Noyes. No date.
    - Note with name and address of Mrs. D. H. Cole. No date.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Lucy Stone. June 2, 1880.
    - Manuscript entitled A Thanksgiving,a poem. By Rose Terry Cooke. No date.
    - To Dr. from K. Sautorn [?]. No Date.
    - Manuscript entitled Unanswered, a poem. By Louise Chandler Moulton. No date.
    - To Dear Friend from A. C. Coxe [?]. Jan. 15, [no year].
    - To William Hayes Ward from Josiah Quincy. August 23, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Dudley Buck. October 22, 1880.
    - To Dear Sir from Josiah Quincy. January 8, 1881.
    - To My Dear Rev. from [unreadable]. October 19, 1880.
    - From William Hayes Ward to Mrs. Jeffries. August 6, 1880.
    - From William Hayes Ward to Miss Jeffries. November 10, 1880.
    - From William Hayes Ward to unknown. No date.
    - To William Hayes Ward from [unreadable]. June 10, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Sarah Woolsey. January 4, 1881.
    - To William Hayes Ward from T. D. Crosby. July 12, 1880.
    - Manuscript of George Eliot, a poem. By Elizabeth Stuart Phelps. January 26, 1881.
    - Manuscript of Sanford R. Gifford,”a poem. By R. H. Stoddard. No date.
    - Signature of E. Simpson, Commodore, United States Navy. No date.
    - Signature of Th. Wilson, Senator from Massachusetts. No date.
    - To Doctor [W. H. Ward] from James Redpath. April 6, 1880.
    - To Henry C. Bowen from Hon. Francis Kernum. November 18, 1880.
    - To My Dear Sir from George F. Hoar. June 30, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from George F. Edmund. June 21, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from George Hepworth. No date.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Ray Palmer. November 13, [no year].
    - To William Hayes Ward from Mary Clemmer. August 24, 1880.
    - To Henry C. Bowen from Hon. Charles W. Jones. November 18, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from N. Porter (Noah). April [7], 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from H. C. Owen. July 23, 1880.
    - To Mr. Bowen from S. B. Chittenden. November 17, 1880.
    - To William Hayesn Ward from T. S. Cuyler. January 22, 1881.
    - To William Hayes Ward from F. S. P. Barnard. August 23, 1880.
    - To Dear Sir from R. S. Storrs. December 21, [no year].
    - To William Hayes Ward from Edward Kimball. May 21, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from James Redpath. June 16, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Neal Dow. November 17, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from James Redpath. February 5, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Sarah Woolsey. March 22, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Helen Hunt Jackson. April 19, [no year].
    - Manuscript for The Yellow Crocus, a poem. By Helen Hunt Jackson. April 22, 1880.
    - To Henry C. Bowen from H. B. Anthony. November 23, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Elizabeth Cady Stanton. May 4, [no year].
    - To William Hayes Ward from Elizabeth Cady Stanton. August 23, [no year].
    - To William Hayes Ward from Celia Thaxter. July 7, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Elizabeth Cady Stanton. September 20, [no year].
    - To William Hayes Ward from Harriet Waters Preston. December 7, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from David Swing. October 14, 1880.
    - Manuscript. Opinion of David Swing regarding ex-presidents becoming senators for life. No date.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Louise Chandler Moulton. March 3, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from A. [?] Coxe. August 19, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from S. C. Bartlett [Samuel C. Bartlett]. July 8, 1880.
    - To Editor of Independent from G. G. Vest. November 27, 1880.
    - To William Hayes Ward from Henry Van Dyke. January 21, 1881.
    - To Henry C. Bowen from William S. Wallace. November 17, 1880.
- Series II: Literary Authors and Papers on American Theater. 1896-1913.
  Includes correspondence of Samuel Chew and Horace Howard Furness, Jr., and Sr. Several letters in this series contain transcriptions that incorrectly attribute the letters of Horace Howard Furness, Jr., to Horace Howard Furness, Sr. and vice versa.
  - John Ruskin. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Letter from John Ruskin. No date.
    - Note that says Ruskin letter to mother [Thom]. No date.
  - Washington Irving. (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Manuscript excerpt from Irving book The Life and Voyages of Christopher Columbus. No date.
    - Transcription of excerpt. No date.
    - Photocopy of the pages of The Life and Voyages of Christopher Columbus that match the handwritten manuscript. No date.
    - Photocopy of Irving's signature from a book. No date.
    - Envelope with letterhead of Norfolk campus of College of William and Mary labeled Washington Irving. December 13, 1962.
  - Papers on American Theater. 1896-1913. (Box-folder 1:27)
    - To Mr. Chew from Julia Marlowe. Feb. 12, 1906.
    - To "Dear Sir" from Sidney Lee. Feb. 16, 1905.
    - To "My Dear Sir" from Henry Irving. Jan. 11, 1896.
    - To "Dear Sir" from R. Garnett. June 15, 1906.
    - From Horace Howard Furness to My dear boy. April 1, 1906.
    - From Horace Howard Furness. Letter to My dear boy. February 21, 1906.
    - From Horace Howard Furness to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. Feb. 13, 1906.
    - From Horace Howard Furness to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. December 17, 1906.
    - From H. H. Furness to "My Dear Sam" [Mr. Chew]. July 28, 1911
    - From Horace Howard Furness, Jr., to Mr. Chew. Feb. 8, 1906.
    - From Horace Howard Furness, Jr. to Mr. Chew. October 19, 1905.
    - Newspaper article, "Tributes Paid to Furness' Memory." No byline. No date.
    - Article about performance given by Mr. E. H. Sothern and Miss Julia Marlowe of Shakespeare's comedy Twelfth Night. No date.
    - Photograph of Dr. Horace Howard Furness, Jr. No date.
    - Envelope with letterhead of Norfolk campus of College of William and Mary marked "Letters removed from S'peare variorum." No date.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. Feb. 26, 1906.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. April 2, 1906.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. Date unreadable.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. Date unreadable.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. August 9, 1912.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. Jul. 22, 1911.
    - Envelope to Mr. Samuel C. Chew. July 28, 1911.
- Series III: Historical Manuscripts and Documents. 1680-1795.
  Includes a printed copy of a speech by Charles II and American colonial documents.
  - Charles II speech. (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Printed copy of speech by King Charles II. Wing C3159. 1680.
  - Permission for Duties. (Box-folder 1:29)
    - For Henry Barrow, Surveyor for the County of Southampton. Signed by Governor Robert Brooke. April 24, 1795.
    - Permission of duties for Henry Barrow approved by president and professors of William and Mary College. March 10, 1795.
  - Land Deed. (Box-folder 1:30)
    - Certifies Thomas Bonyer [?] to land per royal proclamation of 1763. Signed and sealed by Lord Dunmore. Document addressed to surveyor of Fincastle County. Dec. 1, 177[?].
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Literary and Political Correspondence 1930-1936.
  - Kenneth Roberts correspondence. (Box-folder 1:31)
    - Letter from Kenneth Roberts to Elizabeth Urban. No date.
  - S. W. Jackson correspondence. (Box-folder 1:32)
    - To Mr. S. W. Jackson from [Mayberry?]. November 10, 1936.
  - Alexander Robertson correspondence. (Box-folder 1:33)
    - To Mr. Brown from Alexander Robertson. Nov. 30, 1931.
  - Unlabeled manuscript. (Box-folder 1:34)
    - Manuscript appears to be poem, "The Ragpicker" by Thomas Dunn English. No date.
- Series V: William and Mary Norfolk Campus library correspondence. 1958-1960.
  William and Mary Norfolk Campus Correspondence, which includes letters about library collections.
  - W. C. Pollard. (Box-folder 1:35)
    - To Mr. Pollard from Annette Parsons. July 29, 1960.
  - H. B. Grigsby. (Box-folder 1:36)
    - To H. B. Grigsby from P. E. Read. No date.
    - Envelope addressed to Library at William and Mary at Norfolk. Note on envelope says it contains a "letter from H. B. Grigsby book." October 13, 1958.
  - Berkeley Minor correspondence. No date. (Box-folder 1:37)
    - To Miss Emily Christian from Berkeley Minor. October 19, [no year].